New York Association of School Psychologists; Records apap370
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
New York Association of School Psychologists Records
1972-2019
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap370
5.19 cubic ft.
This collections documents the day-to-day activities and operational materials of the New York Association of School Psychologists (NYASP) including administrative materials, event records and resource materials for members.
Box 1
Box 2
Box 3
Box 4
Content Description
This collection includes newsletters, fiscal materials, minutes and agendas, conference materials, administrative materials, correspondence, organization case studies, physical materials, audio-visual materials, screening tools, position papers, legal counsil, legislative lobbying materials, member resource materials, presidential record materials, event planning materials, reports and announcements, and organization history materials.
This collection pertains primarily to records following the consolidation of School Psychologists of Upstate New York (SPUNY), and the New York Association of School Psychologists (NYASP). This consolidation of the two organizations into the New York Association of School Psychologists, NYASP, occurred between 1981 and 1983. While there are some records from this earlier period, they are few in number and primarily pertain to newsletters, member resources, correspondences, and announcements rather than daily operations and activities.
Biographical / Historical
The New York Association of School Psychologists (NYASP) is the organization which represents school psychologists throughout the State. It is divided into geographic chapters, each of which holds local meetings, often with presenters on current issues in the field. As a statewide organization it also holds an annual two and a half day conference. The organization employs a legislative consultant to remain abreast of pending legislation which has an impact upon children, families and schools, and it holds an annual lobby day to meet with state senators and assemblypersons. NYASP publishes a newsletter three or four times a year.
Until 1983 there were two school psychology associations in New York State. NYASP covered the downstate area and the School Psychologists of Upstate New York (SPUNY) covered the remainder. The two organizations then merged into one association, NYASP, occurring between 1981 and 1983.
Acquisition Information
All items in this collection were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives by Ruth Steegmann in 2017 and 2019.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized alphabetically. There are no series.
New York Association of School Psychologists; Education; School Psychologists--New York (State); Correspondence; Publications (Documents); Educational Psychology--New York (State)
- "101 Ways to Praise a Child" NASP Bookmark, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- "2002 Legislative Advocacy Program", Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Administrative Documents, 1984; 1986-1988; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Administrative Documents, 1992; 1995-1996; 1999-2001; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Administrative Documents, 2002-2007; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Administrative Documents, 2011-2013; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Administrative Documents, 2014-2018 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Announces the New SpringerBrief Series: NYASP School Psychology Archives", Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "APA Announces Historic Shift in Position on Masters Level Trained Psychologists", 2019 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Archival Activities for NYASP" Packet, 1991-1992; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Article 153, ca. 2002; 2006; ca. 2010 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Assessment", 1995; 2011-2012; 2014; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "Autism, SPEAK" (1 of 2), 2001; 2006-2007; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "Autism, SPEAK" (2 of 2), 2001; 2006-2007; Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- "Awards", 2003-2005; 2015; Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Awards and Recognition, 2006; 2008; 2012; Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "Background and Fact Sheet on the New York Association of School Psychologists", Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Biographies, 2013; Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Brochures, 1986; 2011; Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Carr Public Affairs Legal Council, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- "'Case Study' Nuts and Bolts of Putting on a Conference. Conference 2012 Niagara Falls" (1 of 2), 2008; 2011-2013; Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- "'Case Study' Nuts and Bolts of Putting on a Conference. Conference 2012 Niagara Falls" (2 of 2), 2008; 2011-2013; Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- "'Case Study' Nuts and Bolts of Putting on a Conference. Conference 2012 Niagara Falls - NYASP Letters for Raffle, etc.", Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- "'Case Study': The Nuts and Bolts of a Presidency. President: Robin Raphael" (1 of 4), 1993; 1998; 2002-2006; 2008-2012; Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- "'Case Study': The Nuts and Bolts of a Presidency. President: Robin Raphael" (2 of 4), 1993; 1998; 2002-2006; 2008-2012; Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- "'Case Study': The Nuts and Bolts of a Presidency. President: Robin Raphael" (3 of 4), 1993; 1998; 2002-2006; 2008-2012; Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- "'Case Study': The Nuts and Bolts of a Presidency. President: Robin Raphael" (4 of 4), 1993; 1998; 2002-2006; 2008-2012; Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Chapter Representative Linda Dugan, 1986-1988; Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- "Comments on Proposed Amendments in Education Law to Create Provisional Bilingual Certification in School Psychology", 2005 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- "Comments on Proposed School Counselor Regulation", 2016 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- "Compliments of Your School Psychologist" Pencil, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- Conference 1985 Materials, Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Conference 1986 Materials, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Conference 1987 Materials, Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Conference 1988 Materials (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Conference 1989 Materials, Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Conference 1990 Materials, 1988; Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Conference 1991 Materials, 1976-1977; 1980-1982; 1984-1991; Undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Conference 1992 Materials, 1987; Undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Conference 1993 Materials, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Conference 1994 Materials, 1983; 1990-1991; 1993-1995; Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Conference 1998 Materials (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Conference 2000 Materials, 1999-2000; Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Conference 2001 Materials, 1994-1995; 1997; Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Conference 2002 Materials (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Conference 2003 Materials, 1999; Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Conference 2004 CD, ca. 2004 (Artifact-box 1)
- Conference 2004 Materials, 1994; 2002-2004; Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Conference 2005 CD, ca. 2005 (Artifact-box 1)
- Conference 2005 Materials, 1999; Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Conference 2006 CD, ca. 2006 (Artifact-box 1)
- Conference 2006 Materials, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Conference 2007 Materials (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Conference 2008 CD, ca. 2008 (Artifact-box 1)
- Conference 2008 Materials, Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Conference 2009 Materials, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Conference 2010 Materials, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Conference 2011 Materials (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Conference 2012 Materials (1 of 4), 2012-2013; Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Conference 2012 Materials (2 of 4), 2012-2013; Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Conference 2012 Materials (3 of 4), 2012-2013; Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Conference 2012 Materials (4 of 4), 2012-2013; Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Conference 2014 Materials, 2009; Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Conference 2015 Materials, Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Conference 2016 Materials (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Conference 2017 Materials (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Conference 2018 Lake Placid Pin, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- Conference 2018 Materials, 2015; 2017-2018; Undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Conference 2021 Materials, Undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
- "Conference Manual 2010", 2008; Undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
- "Constitution of the New York Association of School Psychologists", ca. 1986 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- "Education, Spec. Ed. Law", 2012 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- "Ethics, Prof. Standards", 1986; 1996; Undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Fetal Alcohol Syndrome CD, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- Fetal Alcohol Syndrome Documents, 2009-2010; Undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Fiscal Documents, 1986-2014; Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
- "Funds Sought to Save Mental Health System" Article, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Greenberg Traurig Legal Counsel, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- "Grief Issues at School", Undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
- "History", 1982; 1993; 2014; Undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
- "IDEA", 2004-2005; 2007; Undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
- "Incorporation", 1984; 1991; 2014 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- "Internship", 1984; 1987 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- "It's the Only Dream I know" Article, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Jose P., et. al. v. Ambach, et al., 1987 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- "Learning Disabilities", 2003; Undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Legislative Lobbying Materials and Correspondence, 1986-2018; Undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
- "Legislature", 1996; 2002-2003; 2005; Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- "Licensure", 1991-1992; 2005; 2009; Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
- "Mandate Relief" (1 of 2), 1976-2013; Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- "Mandate Relief" (2 of 2), 1976-2013; Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Member Resource Documents, 2003; 2007; 2009; Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- "Members Want Licensure for Independent Practice - Survey Results", Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- "Membership Application/Colleague Referral", 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- "Membership Directories" (1 of 2), 1985-2004 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- "Membership Directories" (2 of 2), 1985-2004 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- "Mental Health Counseling License Requirements", 2006 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- "MLA", 2007-2010; 2013; Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- NASP Update of Activities and Woodcock-Johnson Psycho-Educational Battery, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Newsletters, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Newsletters, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Newsletters, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Newsletters, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Newsletters, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Newsletters, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Newsletters, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Newsletters, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Newsletters, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Newsletters, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Newsletters, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Newsletters, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Newsletters, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Newsletters, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Newsletters, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Newsletters, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Newsletters, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Newsletters, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Newsletters, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Newsletters, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Newsletters, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Newsletters, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Newsletters, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Newsletters, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Newsletters, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Newsletters, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Newsletters, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Newsletters, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Newsletters, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Newsletters, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Newsletters, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Newsletters, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Newsletters, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Newsletters, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Newsletters, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Newsletters, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Newsletters, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Newsletters, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 50)
- Newsletters, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Newsletters, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Newsletters, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Newsletters, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Newsletters, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Newsletters, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Newsletters, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Newsletters, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Newsletters, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Newsletters, 2014 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Newsletters, 2015 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Newsletters, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Newsletters, 2017 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Newsletters, 2018 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Newsletters, Undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
- "Notes from Retirement Interest Group 'Inaugural Meeting' NASP Convention 2006" (Box 4, Folder 15)
- "NYASP Archival Needs and Activity", 1994 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- "NYASP Chapter C (WNYSPA), D and H" Presentation, Undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
- NYASP Committee: Publication Binder 5/94-9/13, 1989; 1994-2007; 2009-2010; 2012-2013; Undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
- "NYASP Conference 2012 Buffalo, NY" Planning Binder (1 of 2), 2003; 2007-2013; Undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
- "NYASP Conference 2012 Buffalo, NY" Planning Binder (2 of 2), 2003; 2007-2013; Undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
- NYASP Elections, 2014; 2016 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- NYASP Ethics and Standards, 1986; 2006; 2010 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- "NYASP Families and Schools: Together We Can Do Great Things" Sticky Notes, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- "NYASP Historical Video 10/21/09 PSAs Robin Interview" CD, 2009 (Artifact-box 1)
- "NYASP PEC Children First - Addressing Barriers to Learning" CD, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- NYASP Pens and Magnets Bag, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- NYASP Pins Bag, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- NYASP Puck, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- "NYASP School Psychologists' Survival Handbook" Blue Binder, 1984-2002; Undated (Oversize 1)
- "NYASP School Psychologists' Survival Handbook" CD, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- "NYASP School Psychologists' Survival Handbook" Red Binder (1 of 2), 1984-2002; Undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
- "NYASP School Psychologists' Survival Handbook" Red Binder (2 of 2), 1984-2002; Undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
- "NYASP Stopwatch", Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- "NYASP Summer Institute 1993", 1992-1994; Undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
- "NYASP Summer Institute 1993" - Peek'n Peak/Chautauqua Region Planning, 1992-1993; Undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
- NYSUT Representative Assembly and Resolution 56, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- "Operations Handbook", 1996; 2004; Undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Organization Announcements and Correspondences, 1986; ca. 1987; Undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Organization, Committee and Chapter Goals, 2005-2006; Undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
- "OSPA Future Planning Conference", Undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
- "Our Children Are The Future" NYASP Tote Bag, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- "Our Children Are The Future - Today I Feel" NYASP Blue Magnet, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- "Our Children Are The Future - Today I Feel" NYASP Red Magnet, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- "Parental Advisory: Violent Video Games are Not Child's Play", 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- "Paws for Intervention", Undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
- "Position Papers" (1 of 2), 1988-2014; Undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
- "Position Papers" (2 of 2), 1988-2014; Undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
- "Preserving Positions", Undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
- "Preserving Positions", Undated (Flat-file 1)
- "President's Records 2004-2005" (1 of 2), 2001-2006; Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
- "President's Records 2004-2005" (2 of 2), 2001-2006; Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
- "President's Records 2005-2007", Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- "President's Records 2007-2008", 2005-2008; Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
- "Proclamation State of New York Executive Chamber", 1987 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- "Proposed Amendments for School Psychologist Certification", 1993 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- "Putting Children First The Role of School Psychologists in New York's Education Reform" Paper, Undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
- "Questionnaire on State-Level Associations for School Psychologists", 1985 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- "Recent Certification Changes", ca. 2010 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- "Regents State Aid Proposal for School Year 2002-2003", 2001 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- "Request for Proposals (REP) for Editor(s) of NASP Annual Monograph Series to be Published in 1990", Undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
- "RTI", 2006-2007; 2010; Undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
- "School Psychologists - Heroes of Hope", Undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
- "School Psychologists Look Into Your Pupils" NYASP Mug, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- Screening Tool Documents, 1998; 2006-2008; 2012; Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
- "Section 504", 1993; 1999; Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Selections from NYASP Handbook, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Senate Bill S908-D, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- "Specific Learning Disability: Current Approaches to Identification and Proposals for Change", 2003 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- "Summary of Meeting of Western New York School Psychologists Associations (WNYSPA)", Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
- "Summary of School Psychology Liaison Committee Report to Pawny Executive Board, November Meeting", Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
- "Teams", 2005 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- "Test Anxiety" CD, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
- University at Buffalo Graduate Programs, Undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
- WNYSPA Conference 2007 Materials, Undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
- "WNYSPA Fall Conference Dr. Peg Dawson Retention Issues 9/25/92 Chap C" VHS, 1992 (Artifact-box 1)